<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><chapter number="77-7"><catchline>Arrest, by Whom, and How Made</catchline><section number="77-7-1"><histories><history>Enacted by Chapter <modchap sess="1980GS">15</modchap>, 1980 General Session</history><modyear>1980</modyear></histories><catchline>"Arrest" defined -- Restraint allowed.</catchline><tab/>An arrest is an actual restraint of the person arrested or submission to custody. The person shall not be subjected to any more restraint than is necessary for his arrest and detention.
</section><section number="77-7-2"><histories><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="2011GS">18</modchap>, 2011 General Session</history><modyear>2011</modyear><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="2011GS">21</modchap>, 2011 General Session</history><modyear>2011</modyear></histories><catchline>Arrest by peace officers.</catchline><tab/>A peace officer may make an arrest under authority of a warrant or may, without warrant, arrest a person:<subsection number="77-7-2(1)"><subsection number="77-7-2(1)(a)">
for any public offense committed or attempted in the presence of any peace officer; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-2(1)(b)">
as used in this Subsection <xref depth="4" refid="C77-7-S2_1800010118000101" refnumber="77-7-2(1)" start="0">(1)</xref>, "presence" includes all of the physical senses or any device that enhances the acuity, sensitivity, or range of any physical sense, or records the observations of any of the physical senses;</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-2(2)">
when the peace officer has reasonable cause to believe a felony or a class A misdemeanor has been committed and has reasonable cause to believe that the person arrested has committed it;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-2(3)">
when the peace officer has reasonable cause to believe the person has committed a public offense, and there is reasonable cause for believing the person may:
<subsection number="77-7-2(3)(a)">
flee or conceal himself to avoid arrest;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-2(3)(b)">
destroy or conceal evidence of the commission of the offense; or</subsection><subsection number="77-7-2(3)(c)">
injure another person or damage property belonging to another person;</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-2(4)">
when the peace officer has reasonable cause to believe the person has committed the offense of failure to disclose identity under Section <xref depth="3" refid="C76-8-S301.5_1800010118000101" refnumber="76-8-301.5" start="0">76-8-301.5</xref>; or</subsection><subsection number="77-7-2(5)">
when the peace officer has reasonable cause to believe that the person is an alien:
<subsection number="77-7-2(5)(a)">
subject to a civil removal order issued by an immigration judge;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-2(5)(b)">
regarding whom a civil detainer warrant has been issued by the federal Department of Homeland Security; or</subsection><subsection number="77-7-2(5)(c)">
who has been charged or convicted in another state with one or more aggravated felonies as defined by 8 U.S.C. Sec. 1101(a)(43).</subsection></subsection></section><section number="77-7-3"><histories><history>Enacted by Chapter <modchap sess="1980GS">15</modchap>, 1980 General Session</history><modyear>1980</modyear></histories><catchline>By private persons.</catchline><tab/>A private person may arrest another:<subsection number="77-7-3(1)">
For a public offense committed or attempted in his presence; or</subsection><subsection number="77-7-3(2)">
When a felony has been committed and he has reasonable cause to believe the person arrested has committed it.</subsection></section><section number="77-7-4"><histories><history>Enacted by Chapter <modchap sess="1980GS">15</modchap>, 1980 General Session</history><modyear>1980</modyear></histories><catchline>Magistrate may orally order arrest.</catchline><tab/>A magistrate may orally require a peace officer to arrest anyone committing or attempting to commit a public offense in the presence of the magistrate, and, in the case of an emergency, when probable cause exists, a magistrate may orally authorize a peace officer to arrest a person for a public offense, and thereafter, as soon as practical, an information shall be filed against the person arrested.
</section><section number="77-7-5"><histories><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="2019GS">406</modchap>, 2019 General Session</history><modyear>2019</modyear></histories><catchline>Issuance of summons or warrant -- Time and place arrests may be made -- Contents of warrant or summons -- Responsibility for transporting prisoners -- Court clerk to dispense restitution for transportation.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-5(1)">
A magistrate may issue a warrant for arrest in lieu of a summons for the appearance of the accused only upon finding:
<subsection number="77-7-5(1)(a)">
probable cause to believe that the person to be arrested has committed a public offense; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(1)(b)">
under the Utah Rules of Criminal Procedure, and this section that a warrant is necessary to:<subsection number="77-7-5(1)(b)(i)">
prevent risk of injury to a person or property;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(1)(b)(ii)">
secure the appearance of the accused; or</subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(1)(b)(iii)">
protect the public safety and welfare of the community or an individual.</subsection></subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(2)">
If the offense charged is:
<subsection number="77-7-5(2)(a)">
a felony, the arrest upon a warrant may be made at any time of the day or night; or</subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(2)(b)">
a misdemeanor, the arrest upon a warrant can be made at night only if:<subsection number="77-7-5(2)(b)(i)">
the magistrate has endorsed authorization to do so on the warrant;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(2)(b)(ii)">
the person to be arrested is upon a public highway, in a public place, or in a place open to or accessible to the public; or</subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(2)(b)(iii)">
the person to be arrested is encountered by a peace officer in the regular course of that peace officer's investigation of a criminal offense unrelated to the misdemeanor warrant for arrest.</subsection></subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(3)">
For the purpose of Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-5(1)" start="0">(1)</xref>:
<subsection number="77-7-5(3)(a)">
daytime hours are the hours of 6 a.m. to 10 p.m.; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(3)(b)">
nighttime hours are the hours after 10 p.m. and before 6 a.m.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(4)"><subsection number="77-7-5(4)(a)">
If the magistrate determines that the accused must appear in court, the magistrate shall include in the arrest warrant the name of the law enforcement agency in the county or municipality with jurisdiction over the offense charged.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(4)(b)"><subsection number="77-7-5(4)(b)(i)">
The law enforcement agency identified by the magistrate under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-5(4)(a)" start="0">(4)(a)</xref> is responsible for providing inter-county transportation of the defendant, if necessary, from the arresting law enforcement agency to the court site.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(4)(b)(ii)">
The law enforcement agency named on the warrant may contract with another law enforcement agency to have a defendant transported.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(4)(c)"><subsection number="77-7-5(4)(c)(i)">
The law enforcement agency identified by the magistrate under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-5(4)(a)" start="0">(4)(a)</xref> as responsible for transporting the defendant shall provide to the court clerk of the court in which the defendant is tried, an affidavit stating that the defendant was transported, indicating the law enforcement agency responsible for the transportation, and stating the number of miles the defendant was transported.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(4)(c)(ii)">
The court clerk shall account for restitution paid under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="76-3-201(5)" start="0">76-3-201(5)</xref> for governmental transportation expenses and dispense restitution money collected by the court to the law enforcement agency responsible for the transportation of a convicted defendant.</subsection></subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(5)">
The law enforcement agency identified by the magistrate under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-5(4)(a)" start="0">(4)(a)</xref> shall indicate to the court within 48 hours of the issuance, excluding Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays if a warrant issued pursuant to this section is an extradition warrant.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-5(6)">
The law enforcement agency identified by the magistrate under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-5(4)(a)" start="0">(4)(a)</xref> shall report any changes to the status of a warrant issued pursuant to this section to the Bureau of Criminal Identification.</subsection></section><section number="77-7-6"><histories><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="2017GS">43</modchap>, 2017 General Session</history><modyear>2017</modyear></histories><catchline>Manner of making arrest.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-6(1)">
The person making the arrest shall inform the person being arrested of his intention, cause, and authority to arrest him.  Such notice shall not be required when:
<subsection number="77-7-6(1)(a)">
there is reason to believe the notice will endanger the life or safety of the officer or another person or will likely enable the party being arrested to escape;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-6(1)(b)">
the person being arrested is actually engaged in the commission of, or an attempt to commit, an offense; or</subsection><subsection number="77-7-6(1)(c)">
the person being arrested is pursued immediately after the commission of an offense or an escape.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-6(2)"><subsection number="77-7-6(2)(a)">
If a deaf or hard of hearing person, as defined in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="78B-1-201(2)" start="0">78B-1-201(2)</xref>, is arrested for an alleged violation of a criminal law, including a local ordinance, the arresting officer shall assess the communicative abilities of the deaf or hard of hearing person and conduct this notification, and any further notifications of rights, warnings, interrogations, or taking of statements, in a manner that accurately and effectively communicates with the deaf or hard of hearing person, including qualified interpreters, lip reading, pen and paper, typewriters, computers with print-out capability, and telecommunications devices for the deaf.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-6(2)(b)">
Compliance with this Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-6(2)" start="0">(2)</xref> is a factor to be considered by any court when evaluating whether statements of a deaf or hard of hearing person were made knowingly, voluntarily, and intelligently.</subsection></subsection></section><section number="77-7-7"><histories><history>Enacted by Chapter <modchap sess="1980GS">15</modchap>, 1980 General Session</history><modyear>1980</modyear></histories><catchline>Force in making arrest.</catchline><tab/>If a person is being arrested and flees or forcibly resists after being informed of the intention to make the arrest, the person arresting may use reasonable force to effect the arrest. Deadly force may be used only as provided in Section <xref depth="3" refid="C76-2-S404_1800010118000101" refnumber="76-2-404" start="0">76-2-404</xref>.
</section><section number="77-7-8"><histories><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="2015GS">317</modchap>, 2015 General Session</history><modyear>2015</modyear></histories><catchline>Forcible entry to conduct search or make arrest -- Conditions requiring a warrant.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-8(1)"><subsection number="77-7-8(1)(a)">
Subject to Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-8(2)" start="0">(2)</xref>, a peace officer when making an arrest may forcibly enter the building in which the person to be arrested is located, or in which there is probable cause for believing the person to be.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8(1)(b)">
Before making the forcible entry, the officer shall:<subsection number="77-7-8(1)(b)(i)">
identify himself or herself as a law enforcement officer;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8(1)(b)(ii)">
demand admission;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8(1)(b)(iii)">
wait a reasonable period of time for an occupant to admit access; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8(1)(b)(iv)">
explain the purpose for which admission is desired.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-8(1)(c)"><subsection number="77-7-8(1)(c)(i)">
The officer need not give a demand and explanation, or identify himself or herself, before making a forcible entry under the exceptions in Section <xref depth="3" refnumber="77-7-6" start="0">77-7-6</xref> or where there is probable cause to believe evidence will be easily or quickly destroyed.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8(1)(c)(ii)">
The officer shall identify himself or herself and state the purpose for entering the premises as soon as practicable after entering the premises.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-8(1)(d)">
The officer may use only that force which is reasonable and necessary to effectuate forcible entry under this section.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-8(2)">
If the building to be entered under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-8(1)" start="0">(1)</xref> appears to be a private residence or the officer knows the building is a private residence, and if there is no consent to enter or there are no exigent circumstances, the officer shall, before entering the building:
<subsection number="77-7-8(2)(a)">
obtain an arrest or search warrant if the building is the residence of the person to be arrested; or</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8(2)(b)">
obtain a search warrant if the building is a residence, but not the residence of the person whose arrest is sought.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-8(3)">
Notwithstanding any other provision of this chapter, forcible entry under this section may not be made solely for the alleged:
<subsection number="77-7-8(3)(a)">
possession or use of a controlled substance under Section <xref depth="3" refnumber="58-37-8" start="0">58-37-8</xref>; or</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8(3)(b)">
the possession of drug paraphernalia as defined in Section <xref depth="3" refnumber="58-37a-3" start="0">58-37a-3</xref>.</subsection></subsection></section><section number="77-7-8.5"><histories><history>Enacted by Chapter <modchap sess="2014GS">106</modchap>, 2014 General Session</history><modyear>2014</modyear></histories><catchline>Use of tactical groups -- Reporting requirements.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-8.5(1)">
As used in this section:
<subsection number="77-7-8.5(1)(a)"><subsection number="77-7-8.5(1)(a)(i)">
"Reportable incident" means:
<subsection number="77-7-8.5(1)(a)(i)(A)">
the deployment of a tactical group; or</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(1)(a)(i)(B)">
law enforcement officers who serve a search warrant after using forcible entry.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(1)(a)(ii)">
"Reportable incident" does not mean a forced cell entry at a corrections facility.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(1)(b)">
"Tactical group" means a special unit, within a law enforcement agency, specifically trained and equipped to respond to critical, high-risk situations.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)">
On and after January 1, 2015, every state, county, municipal, or other law enforcement agency shall annually on or before April 30 report to the Commission on Criminal and Juvenile Justice the following information for the previous calendar year:
<subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(a)">
whether the law enforcement agency conducted one or more reportable incidents;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)">
the following information regarding each reportable incident:<subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(i)">
the organizational title of the agency, task force, or tactical group deployed;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(ii)">
the city, county, and zip code of the location where the reportable incident occurred;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(iii)">
the reason for the deployment;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(iv)">
the type of warrant obtained, if any;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(v)">
if a threat assessment was completed;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(vi)">
if a warrant was obtained, the name of the judge or magistrate who authorized the warrant;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(vii)">
the number of arrests made, if any;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(viii)">
if any evidence was seized;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(ix)">
if any property was seized, other than property that was seized as evidence;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(x)">
if a forcible entry was made;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(xi)">
if a firearm was discharged by a law enforcement officer, and, if so, approximately how many shots were fired by each officer;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(xii)">
if a weapon was brandished by a person other than the law enforcement officers;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(xiii)">
if a weapon was used by a person against the law enforcement officers and, if a firearm was used, the number or approximate number of shots fired by the person;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(xiv)">
the identity of any law enforcement agencies that participated or provided resources for the deployment;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(xv)">
if a person or domestic animal was injured or killed by a law enforcement officer; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(b)(xvi)">
if a law enforcement officer was injured or killed; and</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(2)(c)">
the number of arrest warrants served that required a forced entry as provided by Section <xref depth="3" refnumber="77-7-8" start="0">77-7-8</xref> and were not served in conjunction with a search warrant that resulted in a reportable incident.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(3)">
If a warrant is served by a multijurisdictional team of law enforcement officers, the reporting requirement in this section shall be the responsibility of the commanding agency or governing authority of the multijurisdictional team.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(4)">
The Commission on Criminal and Juvenile Justice shall develop a standardized format that each law enforcement agency shall use in reporting the data required in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-8.5(2)" start="0">(2)</xref>.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(5)">
A law enforcement agency shall:
<subsection number="77-7-8.5(5)(a)">
compile the data described in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-8.5(2)" start="0">(2)</xref> for each year as a report in the format required under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-8.5(4)" start="0">(4)</xref>; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(5)(b)">
submit the report to:<subsection number="77-7-8.5(5)(b)(i)">
the Commission on Criminal and Juvenile Justice; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(5)(b)(ii)">
the local governing body of the jurisdiction served by the law enforcement agency.</subsection></subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(6)"><subsection number="77-7-8.5(6)(a)">
The Commission on Criminal and Juvenile Justice shall summarize the yearly reports of law enforcement agencies submitted under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-8.5(2)" start="0">(2)</xref>.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(6)(b)">
Before August 1 of each year, the Commission on Criminal and Juvenile Justice shall submit a report of the summaries described in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-8.5(6)(a)" start="0">(6)(a)</xref> to:<subsection number="77-7-8.5(6)(b)(i)">
the attorney general;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(6)(b)(ii)">
the speaker of the House of Representatives, for referral to any house standing or interim committees with oversight of law enforcement and criminal justice;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(6)(b)(iii)">
the president of the Senate, for referral to any senate standing or interim committees with oversight of law enforcement and criminal justice; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(6)(b)(iv)">
each law enforcement agency.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(6)(c)">
The report described in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-8.5(6)(b)" start="0">(6)(b)</xref> shall be published on the Utah Open Government website, open.utah.gov, before August 15 of each year.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(7)"><subsection number="77-7-8.5(7)(a)">
If a law enforcement agency fails to comply with the reporting requirements listed in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-8.5(2)" start="0">(2)</xref>, the Commission on Criminal and Juvenile Justice shall contact the law enforcement agency and request that the agency comply with the required reporting provisions.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-8.5(7)(b)">
If a law enforcement agency fails to comply with the reporting requirements listed in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-8.5(2)" start="0">(2)</xref> within 30 days after being contacted by the Commission on Criminal and Juvenile Justice with a request to comply, the Commission on Criminal and Juvenile Justice shall report the noncompliance to the attorney general, the speaker of the House of Representatives, and the president of the Senate.</subsection></subsection></section><section number="77-7-9"><histories><history>Enacted by Chapter <modchap sess="1980GS">15</modchap>, 1980 General Session</history><modyear>1980</modyear></histories><catchline>Weapons may be taken from prisoner.</catchline><tab/>Any person making an arrest may seize from the person arrested all weapons which he may have on or about his person.
</section><section number="77-7-10"><histories><history>Enacted by Chapter <modchap sess="1980GS">15</modchap>, 1980 General Session</history><modyear>1980</modyear></histories><catchline>Telegraph or telephone authorization of execution of arrest warrant.</catchline><tab/>Any magistrate may, by an endorsement on a warrant of arrest, authorize by telegraph, telephone or other reasonable means, its execution. A copy of the warrant or notice of its issuance and terms may be sent to one or more peace officers. The copy or notice communicated authorizes the officer to proceed in the same manner under it as if he had an original warrant.
</section><section number="77-7-11"><histories><history>Enacted by Chapter <modchap sess="1980GS">15</modchap>, 1980 General Session</history><modyear>1980</modyear></histories><catchline>Possession of warrant by arresting officer not required.</catchline><tab/>Any peace officer who has knowledge of an outstanding warrant of arrest may arrest a person he reasonably believes to be the person described in the warrant, without the peace officer having physical possession of the warrant.
</section><section number="77-7-12"><histories><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="1987GS">245</modchap>, 1987 General Session</history><modyear>1987</modyear></histories><catchline>Detaining persons suspected of shoplifting or library theft -- Persons authorized.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-12(1)">
A peace officer, merchant, or merchant's employee, servant, or agent who has reasonable grounds to believe that goods held or displayed for sale by the merchant have been taken by a person with intent to steal may, for the purpose of investigating the unlawful act and attempting to effect a recovery of the goods, detain the person in a reasonable manner for a reasonable length of time.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-12(2)">
A peace officer or employee of a library may detain a person for the purposes and under the limits of Subsection <xref depth="4" refid="C77-7-S12_1800010118000101" refnumber="77-7-12(1)" start="0">(1)</xref> if there are reasonable grounds to believe the person violated <xref depth="2" refid="C76-6-P8_1800010118000101" refnumber="76-6-8" start="0">Title 76, Chapter 6, Part 8, Library Theft</xref>.</subsection></section><section number="77-7-13"><histories><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="1998GS">282</modchap>, 1998 General Session</history><modyear>1998</modyear></histories><catchline>Arrest without warrant by peace officer -- Reasonable grounds, what constitutes -- Exemption from civil or criminal liability.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-13(1)">
A peace officer may arrest, without warrant, any person the officer has reasonable ground to believe has committed a theft under <xref depth="2" refid="C76-6-P8_1800010118000101" refnumber="76-6-8" start="0">Title 76, Chapter 6, Part 8, Library Theft</xref>, or of goods held or displayed for sale.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-13(2)">
A charge of theft made to a peace officer under <xref depth="2" refid="" refnumber="76-6-8" start="0">Title 76, Chapter 6, Part 8, Library Theft</xref>, by an employee of a library, or by a merchant, merchant's employee, servant, or agent constitutes a reasonable ground for arrest, and the peace officer is relieved from any civil or criminal liability.</subsection></section><section number="77-7-14"><histories><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="1987GS">245</modchap>, 1987 General Session</history><modyear>1987</modyear></histories><catchline>Person causing detention or arrest of person suspected of shoplifting or library theft -- Civil and criminal immunity.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-14(1)">
A peace officer, merchant, or merchant's employee, servant, or agent who causes the detention of a person as provided in Section <xref depth="3" refid="C77-7-S12_1800010118000101" refnumber="77-7-12" start="0">77-7-12</xref>, or who causes the arrest of a person for theft of goods held or displayed for sale, is not criminally or civilly liable where he has reasonable and probable cause to believe the person detained or arrested committed a theft of goods held or displayed for sale.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-14(2)">
A peace officer or employee of a library who causes a detention or arrest of a person under <xref depth="2" refid="C76-6-P8_1800010118000101" refnumber="76-6-8" start="0">Title 76, Chapter 6, Part 8, Library Theft</xref>, is not criminally or civilly liable where he has reasonable and probable cause to believe that the person committed a theft of library materials.</subsection></section><section number="77-7-15"><histories><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="2019GS">411</modchap>, 2019 General Session</history><modyear>2019</modyear></histories><catchline>Authority of peace officer to stop and question suspect -- Grounds.</catchline><tab/>A peace officer may stop any individual in a public place when the officer has a reasonable suspicion to believe the individual has committed or is in the act of committing or is attempting to commit a public offense and may demand the individual's name, address, date of birth, and an explanation of the individual's actions.</section><section number="77-7-16"><histories><history>Enacted by Chapter <modchap sess="1980GS">15</modchap>, 1980 General Session</history><modyear>1980</modyear></histories><catchline>Authority of peace officer to frisk suspect for dangerous weapon -- Grounds.</catchline><tab/>A peace officer who has stopped a person temporarily for questioning may frisk the person for a dangerous weapon if he reasonably believes he or any other person is in danger.
</section><section number="77-7-17"><histories><history>Enacted by Chapter <modchap sess="1980GS">15</modchap>, 1980 General Session</history><modyear>1980</modyear></histories><catchline>Authority of peace officer to take possession of weapons.</catchline><tab/>A peace officer who finds a dangerous weapon pursuant to a frisk may take and keep it until the completion of the questioning, at which time he shall either return it if lawfully possessed, or arrest such person.
</section><section number="77-7-17.5"><histories><history>Enacted by Chapter <modchap sess="2019GS">462</modchap>, 2019 General Session</history><modyear>2019</modyear></histories><catchline>Physical body cavity search policy -- Requirements.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-17.5(1)">
As used in this section:
<subsection number="77-7-17.5(1)(a)">
"Arrestee" means an individual who is in the custody of law enforcement for an offense for which the individual has not been convicted.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(1)(b)"><subsection number="77-7-17.5(1)(b)(i)">
"Body cavity" includes the anus, rectum, vagina, esophagus, or stomach.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(1)(b)(ii)">
"Body cavity" does not include the mouth, ear canal, or nasal passages.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(1)(c)"><subsection number="77-7-17.5(1)(c)(i)">
"Physical body cavity search" means a search of a body cavity of an individual that involves touching the individual with:
<subsection number="77-7-17.5(1)(c)(i)(A)">
any part of another individual's body; or</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(1)(c)(i)(B)">
an instrument or other item.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(1)(c)(ii)">
"Physical body cavity search" does not include a clothed, pat down search.</subsection></subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(2)">
Each county jail shall adopt and implement a policy that meets the minimum standards contained in a model policy established by the Commission on Criminal and Juvenile Justice.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)">
The model policy shall specify the minimum standards and procedures to be followed by the county jail when a body cavity search is performed on an arrestee within the county jail's jurisdiction, including:
<subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(a)">
stating with specificity the circumstances under which a body cavity search may be performed on an arrestee;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(b)">
designating who may authorize the performance of a body cavity search;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(c)">
designating specific jail staff or medical personnel who may perform a body cavity search;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(d)">
requiring any nonmedically trained jail staff who may perform a body cavity search to be trained on safe practices for conducting a body cavity search;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(e)">
requiring documentation of each body cavity search performed at the correctional facility, including:<subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(e)(i)">
the identity of the arrestee searched;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(e)(ii)">
the date, time, and location of the search;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(e)(iii)">
the identity of the individual performing the search;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(e)(iv)">
the identity of the individual authorizing the search;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(e)(v)">
a description of the body areas searched and the procedures followed in performing the search; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(e)(vi)">
the circumstances necessitating the body cavity search; and</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(f)">
designating rules and procedures to be followed, by authorized staff, when performing a body cavity search that account for the health and privacy interests of the arrestee, including:<subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(f)(i)">
the location where a body cavity search must be performed;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(f)(ii)">
the gender requirements of the individuals who perform or observe the search in relation to the gender of the arrestee being searched; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(3)(f)(iii)">
methods to ensure the body cavity search is conducted with the minimal amount of touching necessary to effectuate the purposes of the search.</subsection></subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-17.5(4)">
A county jail's body cavity search policy is a public record.</subsection></section><section number="77-7-18"><histories><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="2018GS">379</modchap>, 2018 General Session</history><modyear>2018</modyear></histories><catchline>Citation on misdemeanor or infraction charge.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-18(1)">
Any person subject to arrest or prosecution on a misdemeanor or infraction charge may be issued and delivered a citation that requires the person to appear at the court of the magistrate with territorial jurisdiction.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-18(2)">
The following may issue the citation described in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-18(1)" start="0">(1)</xref>:
<subsection number="77-7-18(2)(a)">
a peace officer, in lieu of or in addition to taking the person into custody;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-18(2)(b)">
any public official of any county or municipality charged with the enforcement of the law;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-18(2)(c)">
a port-of-entry agent as defined in Section <xref depth="3" refnumber="72-1-102" start="0">72-1-102</xref>;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-18(2)(d)">
an animal control officer of a county, municipality, or special service district under <xref depth="1" refnumber="17D-1" start="0">Title 17D, Chapter 1, Special Service District Act</xref>, who is authorized to provide animal control service; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-18(2)(e)">
a volunteer authorized to issue a citation under Section <xref depth="3" refnumber="41-6a-217" start="0">41-6a-217</xref>.</subsection></subsection></section><section number="77-7-19"><histories><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="2009GS">292</modchap>, 2009 General Session</history><modyear>2009</modyear></histories><catchline>Appearance required by citation -- Arrest for failure to appear -- Transfer of cases -- Motor vehicle violations -- Disposition of fines and costs.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-19(1)">
A person receiving a citation issued pursuant to Section <xref depth="3" refid="C77-7-S18_1800010118000101" refnumber="77-7-18" start="0">77-7-18</xref> shall appear before the magistrate designated in the citation on or before the time and date specified in the citation unless the uniform bail schedule adopted by the Judicial Council or Subsection <xref depth="4" refid="C77-7-S21_1800010118000101" refnumber="77-7-21(1)" start="0">77-7-21(1)</xref> permits forfeiture of bail for the offense charged.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-19(2)">
A citation may not require a person to appear sooner than five days or later than 14 days following its issuance.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-19(3)"><subsection number="77-7-19(3)(a)">
A person who receives a citation and who fails to comply with Section <xref depth="3" refid="C77-7-S21_1800010118000101" refnumber="77-7-21" start="0">77-7-21</xref> on or before the time and date and at the court specified is subject to arrest.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-19(3)(b)">
The magistrate may issue a warrant of arrest based upon a citation that was served and filed in accordance with Section <xref depth="3" refid="C77-7-S20_1800010118000101" refnumber="77-7-20" start="0">77-7-20</xref>.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-19(4)">
Except where otherwise provided by law, a citation or information issued for violations of <xref depth="0" refid="C41_1800010118000101" refnumber="41" start="0">Title 41, Motor Vehicles</xref>, shall state that the person receiving the citation or information shall appear before the magistrate who has jurisdiction over the offense charged.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-19(5)">
Any justice court judge may, upon the motion of either the defense attorney or prosecuting attorney, based on a lack of territorial jurisdiction or the disqualification of the judge, transfer cases to a justice court with territorial jurisdiction or the district court within the county.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-19(6)"><subsection number="77-7-19(6)(a)">
Clerks and other administrative personnel serving the courts shall ensure that all citations for violation of <xref depth="0" refid="C41_1800010118000101" refnumber="41" start="0">Title 41, Motor Vehicles</xref>, are filed in a court with jurisdiction and venue and shall refuse to receive citations that should be filed in another court.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-19(6)(b)">
Fines, fees, costs, and forfeitures imposed or collected for violations of <xref depth="0" refid="C41_1800010118000101" refnumber="41" start="0">Title 41, Motor Vehicles</xref>, which are filed contrary to this section shall be paid to the entitled municipality or county by the state, county, or municipal treasurer who has received the fines, fees, costs, or forfeitures from the court which collected them.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-19(6)(c)">
The accounting and remitting of sums due shall be at the close of the fiscal year of the municipality or county which has received fines, fees, costs, or forfeitures as a result of any improperly filed citations.</subsection></subsection></section><section number="77-7-20"><histories><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="2018GS">309</modchap>, 2018 General Session</history><modyear>2018</modyear></histories><catchline>Service of citation on defendant -- Filing in court -- Electronic filing -- Contents of citations.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-20(1)">
Except as provided in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-20(4)" start="0">(4)</xref>, a peace officer or public official who issues a citation pursuant to Section <xref depth="3" refnumber="77-7-18" start="0">77-7-18</xref> shall give the citation to the individual cited and shall within five business days electronically file the data from Subsections <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-20(2)(a)" start="0">(2)(a)</xref> through <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-20(2)(g)" start="0">(2)(g)</xref> with the court specified in the citation.  The data transmission shall use the court's electronic filing interface.  A nonconforming filing is not effective.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(2)">
The citation issued under authority of this chapter shall contain the following data:
<subsection number="77-7-20(2)(a)">
the name of the court before which the individual is to appear;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(2)(b)">
the name of the individual cited;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(2)(c)">
a brief description of the offense charged;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(2)(d)">
the date, time, and place at which the offense is alleged to have occurred;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(2)(e)">
the date on which the citation was issued;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(2)(f)">
the name of the peace officer or public official who issued the citation, and the name of the arresting individual if an arrest was made by a private party and the citation was issued in lieu of taking the arrested individual before a magistrate;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(2)(g)">
the time and date on or before and after which the individual is to appear or a statement that the court will notify the individual of the time to appear;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(2)(h)">
the address of the court in which the individual is to appear;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(2)(i)">
whether the offense is a domestic violence offense; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(2)(j)">
a notice containing substantially the following language:<eol/><center>READ CAREFULLY</center><eol/><tab/>This citation is not an information and will not be used as an information without your consent.  If an information is filed you will be provided a copy by the court.  You MUST appear in court on or before the time set in this citation or as directed by the court.  IF YOU FAIL TO APPEAR, THE COURT MAY ISSUE A WARRANT FOR YOUR ARREST.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(3)">
By electronically filing the data with the court, the peace officer or public official certifies to the court that:
<subsection number="77-7-20(3)(a)">
the citation or information, including the summons and complaint, was served upon the defendant in accordance with the law;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(3)(b)">
the defendant committed the offense set forth in the served documents; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(3)(c)">
the court to which the defendant was directed to appear is the proper court pursuant to Section <xref depth="3" refnumber="77-7-21" start="0">77-7-21</xref>.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(4)"><subsection number="77-7-20(4)(a)">
If a citing law enforcement officer is not reasonably able to access the efiling system, the citation need not be filed electronically if being filed with a justice court.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(4)(b)">
The court may accept an electronic filing received after five business days if:<subsection number="77-7-20(4)(b)(i)">
the defendant consents to the filing; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-20(4)(b)(ii)">
the court finds the interests of justice would be best served by accepting the filing.</subsection></subsection></subsection></section><section number="77-7-21"><histories><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="2009GS">292</modchap>, 2009 General Session</history><modyear>2009</modyear></histories><catchline>Proceeding on citation -- Voluntary forfeiture of bail -- Parent signature required -- Information, when required.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-21(1)"><subsection number="77-7-21(1)(a)">
A copy of the citation issued under Section <xref depth="3" refid="C77-7-S18_1800010118000101" refnumber="77-7-18" start="0">77-7-18</xref> that is filed with the magistrate may be used in lieu of an information to which the person cited may plead guilty or no contest and be sentenced or on which bail may be forfeited.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-21(1)(b)">
With the magistrate's approval, a person may voluntarily forfeit bail without appearance being required in any case of a class B misdemeanor or less.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-21(1)(c)">
Voluntary forfeiture of bail shall be entered as a conviction and treated the same as if the accused pleaded guilty.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-21(1)(d)">
If the person cited is under 18 years of age, and if any of the charges allege a violation of <xref depth="0" refid="C41_1800010118000101" refnumber="41" start="0">Title 41, Motor Vehicles</xref>, the court shall promptly mail a copy of the citation or a notice of the citation to the address as shown on the citation, to the attention of the parent or guardian of the defendant.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-21(2)">
An information shall be filed and proceedings held in accordance with the Rules of Criminal Procedure and all other applicable provisions of this code if the person cited  pleads not guilty to the offense charged.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-21(3)"><subsection number="77-7-21(3)(a)">
The information is an original pleading.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-21(3)(b)">
If a person cited waives by written agreement the filing of the information, the prosecution may proceed on the citation.</subsection></subsection></section><section number="77-7-23"><histories><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="2018GS">140</modchap>, 2018 General Session</history><modyear>2018</modyear></histories><catchline>Delivery of prisoner arrested without warrant to magistrate -- Transfer to court with jurisdiction -- Transfer of duties -- Violation as misdemeanor.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-23(1)"><subsection number="77-7-23(1)(a)">
When an arrest is made without a warrant by a peace officer or private person, the person arrested shall be taken without unnecessary delay to the magistrate in the district court, the precinct of the county, or the municipality in which the offense occurred, except under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-23(2)" start="0">(2)</xref>.  An information stating the charge against the person shall be made before the magistrate.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-23(1)(b)">
If the justice court judge of the precinct or municipality or the district court judge is not available, the arrested person shall be taken before the magistrate within the same county who is nearest to the scene of the alleged offense or nearest to the jail under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-23(2)" start="0">(2)</xref>, who may act as committing magistrate for arraigning the accused, setting bail, or issuing warrants.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-23(2)"><subsection number="77-7-23(2)(a)">
If the arrested person under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-23(1)" start="0">(1)</xref> must be transported from jail to a magistrate, the person may be taken before the magistrate nearest to the jail rather than the magistrate specified in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-23(1)" start="0">(1)</xref> for arraignment, setting bail, or issuing warrants.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-23(2)(b)">
The case shall then be transferred to the court having jurisdiction.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-23(3)">
If a jail accepts custody of a person arrested under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-23(1)" start="0">(1)</xref>, the duties under this section of the peace officer or private person who makes the arrest are transferred to the jail and the jail's personnel.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-23(4)">
This section does not confer jurisdiction upon a court unless otherwise provided by law.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-23(5)">
Any officer or person violating this section is guilty of a class B misdemeanor.</subsection></section><section number="77-7-24"><histories><history>Renumbered and Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="2005GS">2</modchap>, 2005 General Session</history><modyear>2005</modyear></histories><catchline>Notice to appear in court -- Contents -- Promise to comply -- Signing -- Release from custody -- Official misconduct.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-24(1)">
If a person  who is arrested for a  violation of <xref depth="1" refid="C41-6a_1800010118000101" refnumber="41-6a" start="0">Title 41, Chapter 6a, Traffic Code</xref>, that is punishable as a misdemeanor is immediately taken before a magistrate as provided under Section <xref depth="3" refid="C77-7-S23_1800010118000101" refnumber="77-7-23" start="0">77-7-23</xref>, the peace officer shall prepare, in triplicate or more copies, a written notice to appear in court containing:
<subsection number="77-7-24(1)(a)">
the name and address of the person;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-24(1)(b)">
the number, if any, of the person's driver license;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-24(1)(c)">
the license plate number of the person's vehicle;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-24(1)(d)">
the offense charged; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-24(1)(e)">
the time and place the person shall appear in court.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-24(2)">
The time specified in the notice to appear must be at least five days after the arrest of the person unless the person demands an earlier hearing.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-24(3)">
The place specified in the notice to appear shall be made before a magistrate of competent jurisdiction in the county in which the alleged violation occurred.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-24(4)"><subsection number="77-7-24(4)(a)">
In order to secure release as provided in this section, the arrested person shall promise to appear in court by signing at least one copy of the written notice prepared by the arresting officer.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-24(4)(b)">
The arresting peace officer shall immediately:<subsection number="77-7-24(4)(b)(i)">
deliver a copy of the notice to the person promising to appear; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-24(4)(b)(ii)">
release the person arrested from custody.</subsection></subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-24(5)">
A peace officer violating any of the provisions of this section shall be:
<subsection number="77-7-24(5)(a)">
guilty of misconduct in office; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-24(5)(b)">
subject to removal from office.</subsection></subsection></section><section number="77-7-25"><histories><history>Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="2016GS">33</modchap>, 2016 General Session</history><modyear>2016</modyear></histories><catchline>Keeping of records -- Making and forwarding of abstract upon conviction or forfeiture of bail -- Form and contents  -- Official misconduct.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-25(1)">
A magistrate or judge of a court shall keep a full record of each case in which a person is charged with:
<subsection number="77-7-25(1)(a)">
a violation of this chapter; or</subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(1)(b)">
any other law regulating the operation of a motor vehicle on the highway.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(2)"><subsection number="77-7-25(2)(a)">
Within five days after the conviction or forfeiture of bail of a person on a charge of violating a provision of this chapter or other law regulating the operation of a motor vehicle on the highway, the magistrate of the court or clerk of the court in which the conviction was made or bail was forfeited shall prepare and immediately forward to the department an abstract of the record of the court covering the case in which the person was convicted or forfeited bail.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(2)(b)">
The abstract shall be certified by the person required to prepare the abstract to be true and correct.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(2)(c)">
A report under this Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-25(2)" start="0">(2)</xref> is not required for a conviction involving the illegal parking or standing of a vehicle.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(3)">
The abstract must be made in a manner specified by the Driver License Division and shall include the:
<subsection number="77-7-25(3)(a)">
name and address of the party charged;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(3)(b)">
number, if any, of the person's driver license;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(3)(c)">
license plate number of the vehicle involved;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(3)(d)">
nature of the offense;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(3)(e)">
date of hearing;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(3)(f)">
plea;</subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(3)(g)">
judgment, or whether bail was forfeited; and</subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(3)(h)">
amount of the fine or forfeiture.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(4)">
A court shall provide a copy of the report to the Driver License Division on the conviction of a person of manslaughter or other felony in which a vehicle was used.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(5)">
The failure, refusal, or neglect of a judicial officer to comply with the requirements of this section constitutes misconduct in office and is grounds for removal.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-25(6)">
The Driver License Division shall classify and disclose all abstracts received in accordance with Section <xref depth="3" refnumber="53-3-109" start="0">53-3-109</xref>.</subsection></section><section number="77-7-26"><histories><history>Renumbered and Amended by Chapter <modchap sess="2005GS">2</modchap>, 2005 General Session</history><modyear>2005</modyear></histories><catchline>Improper disposition or cancellation of notice to appear or traffic citation -- Official misconduct -- Misdemeanor.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-26(1)"><subsection number="77-7-26(1)(a)">
It is unlawful and official misconduct for any peace officer or other officer or public employee to dispose of:<subsection number="77-7-26(1)(a)(i)">
a notice to appear; or</subsection><subsection number="77-7-26(1)(a)(ii)">
traffic citation.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-26(1)(b)">
The provisions of Subsection <xref depth="4" refid="C77-7-S26_1800010118000101" refnumber="77-7-26(1)(a)" start="0">(1)(a)</xref> do not apply if the disposal is done with the consent of the magistrate before whom the arrested person was to appear.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-26(2)">
A person who cancels or solicits the cancellation of a notice to appear or a traffic citation, in any manner other than as provided by law, is guilty of a class B misdemeanor.</subsection></section><section number="77-7-27"><histories><history>Enacted by Chapter <modchap sess="2018GS">289</modchap>, 2018 General Session</history><modyear>2018</modyear></histories><catchline>Quotas for arrest, citation prohibited.</catchline><subsection number="77-7-27(1)">
As used in this section:
<subsection number="77-7-27(1)(a)">
"Law enforcement agency" means an entity of the state, or a political subdivision of the state, that exists primarily to prevent and detect crime and enforce criminal laws, statutes, or ordinances.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-27(1)(b)">
"Law enforcement quota" means any requirement or minimum standard regarding the number or percentage of citations or arrests made by a law enforcement officer.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="77-7-27(2)">
A political subdivision or law enforcement agency employing a peace officer may not require or direct that a peace officer meet a law enforcement quota.</subsection><subsection number="77-7-27(3)">
Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="77-7-27(2)" start="0">(2)</xref> does not prohibit a political subdivision or law enforcement agency from including a peace officer's engagement with the community or enforcement activity as part of an overall determination of the peace officer's performance.</subsection></section></chapter>
